A Guide to the Henkel Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8653-f
Henkel Family Papers 1805-1941
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8653-f
ca. 475 items
Mrs. John Godfrey Miller
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the Library by Mrs. John Godfrey Miller of New Market, Virginia, through Dr. H.E. Comstock of Winchester, Virginia, on November 21, 1989.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This addition to the papers of the Henkel family of New Market, Virginia, consists of ca. 475 items (4 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2 linear feet), 1805-1941, and contains correspondence, business and legal papers, genealogical material, account books, photographs, notes, block cuts, subscription lists, minute books, printed material, and manuscripts.
The nineteenth century correspondents of the Henkel family are listed alphabetically in the folder listing section of this guide beginning on page five with a brief note concerning the content of the letters. Mr. John G. Stewart, retired professor of James Madison University, has supplied notes concerning the content of those letters in German. Most of the correspondence was addressed to Dr. Solomon Henkel and Dr. Samuel G. Henkel.
The correspondence of the Henkel Family Association contains the following topics: a discussion about the inscriptions on the Hinkle Fort monument and the memorial for John Justus Henckel with notes on the history of Hinkle's Fort and John Justus Henckel(1935 Aug 21); remarks concerning Christina Hinkle and Isaac Harmon upon the unveiling of the monument to John Justus Henckel by J.W. Harmon of Parsons, West Virginia(1937 Jan 25); Jacob Henkel's property in West Virginia(1937 Sep 20); information regarding Angeline Miller and Adam Sheets(1940 Jan 6); and Jacob Hinkle, son of George Rudolphus Hinkle(1940 Jan 11).
Some items in the business and legal papers include a memorandum of type to be secured in Baltimore(1826 Oct 15); the attempt to purchase a "boalting cloth No. 8" for use in John Coiner's flour mill (1834 Jun 3); a fine for Samuel G. Henkel's non-attendance at the regimental muster in Captain Neff's Company (1839); plans for Godfred Hinkle's barn (1840 Feb 20); a Land Office Treasury Warrant # 18063 to Samuel G. Henkel for 590 acres (1849 Nov 26); Solomon Henkel's memorandum book with notes for the settling of his estate (1856 Feb 28); a bill of type to be secured in Baltimore at Spaldings (1837 Apr 26); typed copies of Henkel family land patents, surveys, and deeds in Virginia and West Virginia(n.d.).
Genealogical materials include a Conrad family and Keyser family notebook (1917); a "family record of Henkel Stock" as copied by Dr. C.C. Henkel and Rev. D.M. Henkel, partially related by Dr. Solomon Henkel(n.d.); and miscellaneous notes and manuscripts concerning the Henkel family.
Miscellaneous papers contains notes about Rev. Reck's sermons taken by [ Samuel G. Henkel] (1825); a phrenological analysis of the head of Samuel G. Henkel(1841 Apr 2); the marriage certificate of Gideon Koiner and Rebecca M. Henkel(1853 Nov 14); a qualitative analysis of a sample of water made by University of Virginia Professor J.W. Mallet(1892 Oct 15); the historical address "One Army of the Living God" given before the Henkel Memorial Association in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, concerning the contributions of the Henkel Family(1917); minutes of the Henkel Memorial Association(n.d.); and an engraving of a printing press patented by Peter Smith and manufactured by Robert Hoe and Company, New York(n.d.).
Also present are three bound volumes of records pertaining to the New Market Academy, including minutes, subscription lists, resignation letters of its professors, and other loose material found in the volumes, 1838-1941. Dr. Solomon Henkel was one of the original Trustees appointed on February 21, 1817, when the New Market Academy was incorporated. The Henkel family has been represented on the Board of Trustees of the New Market Academy throughout its history by such men as Samuel G. Henkel and C.C. Henkel.
Photographs include those of Dr. [ Casper Henkel]; Barbara Teter Henkel; a page from the diary of Rev. H.M. Muhlenberg concerning Rev. Anthony Jacob Henkel; the Hinkle Fort built by Justus Henckel; two houses built by Abraham Henckel; the memorial monument to John Justus Henckel, Sr.; sons of Dr. Solomon Henkel; Rev. Paul Henkel and his wife, Elizabeth Nagley Henkel; and the sons of Rev. Paul Henkel.
Most of the printed material is described in the folder listing part of this guide.
Organization
This collection has been divided into two alphabetical series: 1) Correspondence and 2) Miscellaneous Papers. The nineteenth century correspondence has been arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. The miscellaneous papers have been arranged according to type of material.
Container List
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE
  - A: NINETEENTH CENTURY CORRESPONDENTS
    * indicates some or all documents are in German
    - John C. Alberti* to Solomon Henkel, 1821 Apr 25 (Box Box 1)
      re his absence in Germany and his instructions that his mail be sent to Solomon Henkel where he will pick it up on his return to the United States
    - Charles Albertina* to Solomon Henkel, 1812 Dec 28 (Box Box 1)
      re his need of medical supplies as he is a physician
    - Robert Allen to Samuel G. Henkel, 1842 Dec 29 (Box Box 1)
      re financial provision for his aunt, Mrs. Duff
    - Jacob W. Barger to Samuel G. Henkel, 1849 Mar 28 (Box Box 1)
      re his preparations for sailing to California
    - Charles Beazley to Samuel G. Henkel, 1847 Aug 9 (Box Box 1)
      re the improvements in his health, rumors of the death of Solomon Henkel, and a fire engine for sale
    - Charles Berry to Samuel G. Henkel, 1833 Apr 2 (Box Box 1)
      re arrangements for a cataract operation
    - [Absalom Brown] to Samuel G. Henkel, n.y. Feb 2 (Box Box 1)
      re Mr. Yeager's misrepresentation of his statements concerning the Tennessee Synod in The Observer
    - George W. Carpenter to Samuel G. Henkel, 1830 Aug 2 (Box Box 1)
      re his supply of medical instruments and models with their cost
    - William Carpenter* to Dr. [Solomon ?] Henkel, 1809-1813 (Box Box 1)
      his letters include: a list of elders and officers of the Hebron Church, Madison County (1809 Jun); his difficulties in attending Special Conference, books sent for sale, and a discussion of methods of payment (1809 Sep 14); his trip to Ohio, and his request to Paul or Phillip Henkel to preach in his church and also at the Reformed Church (1810 Aug 22); acknowledgement of the receipt of some medicine and mention of the good acceptance of the Song Book by the congregation (1811 Mar 9); difficulties in obtaining Conference Reports and description of his sickness (1811 Apr 1); approval of new Catechism, and requests information re next Special Conference (1812 Feb 3); discussion of the possibility of the Henkel Press printing Arndt's "Wahres Christenthum" in English (1812 Apr 8); necessity of a personal meeting with Paul Henkel (1812 Sep 11); and mention of Solomon Henkel as agent for Johann Gruber in Hagerstown, and The Evangelical Magazine printed in Philadelphia (1813 Mar 8).
    - Kasper Coiner* to Samuel G. and Ambrose Henkel, 1836-1838 (Box Box 1)
      re money matters and the purchase of a horse
    - Kasper Coiner, John Leonard, David Coiner, and Jacob Kinnard*, 1833-1846 (Box Box 1)
      re the formation of a new Synod, testimonial for Rev. J. Killian, and the need for attention to the literary qualifications for aspiring young ministers
    - Conrad Lucas & Company to Solomon Henkel, 1810 Nov 9 (Box Box 1)
      re his order for a Cycl[opedia]
    - Martin Coyner to Susan Henkel, 1875, 1879 (Box Box 1)
      re money sent to the post office and the failing health of all three of her brothers, Martin, David, and Simon
    - Joseph Creutz* to Solomon Henkel, 1812, 1816 (Box Box 1)
      difficulties re taxes and land formerly owned by Johannes Henkel (1812 Sep 20); and questions re sale of land and request for advice (1816 May 16)
    - Jacob Crigler* to Solomon Henkel, 1816 (Box Box 1)
      death of two of his sons due to dysentery, wife and slave both in serious condition (Feb 16) and the introduction of English Song Books in Madison County (Jul 22)
    - Henry Deifenbach* to Solomon Henkel, 1806-1815 (Box Box 1)
      request for books and a proposal for transporting them (1806 Oct 11); his interest in subscription to a New Market newspaper and detailed description of a deadly disease on the rampage in North Carolina (1807 Oct 11); while in Staunton sends announcement that he wishes to preach in New Market on June 25 th (1815 Jun 20)
    - John Dreher* to Solomon Henkel, 1813 May 7 (Box Box 1)
      difficulties in recruiting preachers, the need for outsiders to come to [South Carolina ?], and business matters
    - Godfrey Drehr to Solomon Henkel, 1813 Jun 14 (Box Box 1)
      re an order for books about Martin Luther, the Augsburg Confession, Catechisms, and hymn books in English and German to be sent to Saluda, S.C., inroads made by other denominations in South Carolina and David Henkel's work there
    - Robert M. [Fleet ?] to Catherine Zirkle, 1844 Mar 28 (Box Box 1)
      re expressions of his love
    - Samuel Fleischman* to Solomon Henkel, 1810 May 8 (Box Box 1)
      request for books including two dozen catechisms for teaching purposes
    - George Flohr* to Solomon Henkel, 1807-1823 (Box Box 1)
      difficulties in attending the Special Conference in New Market because of distance and pastoral duties (1807 Sep 12); a list of officers, Lutheran and Reformed, and the location of churches in Wythe, Montgomery, and Greenbriar Counties (1809 Oct 18); receipt of catechisms and their success as a teaching tool (1809 Oct); detailed and lengthy manuscript of a Lutheran Catechism, and its differences with Reformed beliefs (1810 Dec 22); explanation and commentary re Catechism (1811 Feb 16); suggestions re the new Lutheran Catechism (1811 Jul 30); urgent request for more English Catechisms, saying more than 200 could be sold, if available, and interest in applying for Pastor Carpenter's job in Madison County (1814 Apr 14); request for more English Catechisms (1819 Sep 14); account of books (1820 Feb 5); requests more first edition catechisms, recommends the bank notes from the Union Bank of Alexandria or the North Carolina Treasury bills for paying notes (1820 Apr 1); requests clarification of his account (1820 Jun 24); requests for more catechisms, concern with his book account and mention of the South Carolina State Bank (1821 Sep 1; 1822 Jun 3 Aug 4; & Dec 18); warning about a so-called preacher by the name of Miller, known for his drinking and carousing, [who ?] will be in New Market soon and will want to buy a horse to ride back to Pennsylvania (1823 Jan 24).
    - Henry Fry* to Solomon Henkel, 1819, 1822 (Box Box 1)
      money transactions with Henkel's brother-in-law Miller in Winchester (1819 Jan 19); and requests for Henkel to mediate between two parties re land transactions (1822 Dec 23)
    - William Fulmer to Samuel Fulmer, 1874 Jan 1 (Box Box 1)
      re family news
    - Joseph Funk* to [Solomon Henkel ?], 1816 Aug 12 (Box Box 1)
      request to expedite the binding of the Song Books as he will be in New Market on the following Saturday
    - Jacob Garst* to Solomon Henkel, 1812-1813 (Box Box 1)
      difficulties in receiving mail (1812 Jun 18)
    - William Gosen* to [Solomon] Henkel, 1811 Jul 1 (Box Box 1)
      transaction involving the trading of 2/6 nails for Song Books in New Market
    - Jacob Grison* to Solomon Henkel, 1812 Jan 8 (Box Box 1)
      lengthy remarks re the new Catechism and his own personal observations
    - Samuel Grosh* to Solomon Henkel, 1811 (Box Box 1)
      J.O. Kramer of Maytown, North Carolina, has two dozen copies of a book which Henkel wants (Jul 30); reference to previous letter and the sale of books (Sep 4); acknowlegement of the receipt of books (Nov 14)
    - Frederick Haas* to Solomon Henkel, [1815] (Box Box 1)
      requests for German catechisms
    - Samuel Hahn* to Solomon Henkel, 1815-1816 (Box Box 1)
      request for German Bible (1815 Dec 5); and business transactions re books (1816 Dec 8)
    - Henry Christopher Hahn and Jacob Hahn* to Solomon Henkel, 1810, 1821 (Box Box 1)
      account of books (1810) and book transactions and a list of subscribers to a book (1821)
    - Ernest L. [Hazelius ?] to George Boggs, 1839 Jul 4 (Box Box 1)
      re his refusal to get involved in political questions, favoring a complete separation of church and state, as does the Lutheran Church and the Society for the Promotion of Christian Union
    - Henry Christian Helmuth* to Solomon Henkel, 1805, 1817, 1820 (Box Box 1)
      Request for a subscription for a church proposal (1805); his acknowledgement of the influence of Henkel on the writing of a small book by Helmuth (1817); the cessation of the The Evangelical Magazine and his recommendation of Pastor Plitt's new magazine (1820)
    - [Ambrose Henkel ?]* to Casper Koiner, 1832 Mar 26 (Box Box 1)
    - Gideon Henkel* to Solomon Henkel, 1812 Dec 9 (Box Box 1)
      arrival in Point Pleasant and his great difficulty in learning German
    - Ireneus N. Henkel to Samuel G. Henkel, 1831-1832 (Box Box 1)
      re a list of articles that he wants him to get for him, the isolation of their home from society, Ambrose's success in selling medicines and books on commission, the success of other businessmen, the desire of the German people to educate their children, his neighbors desire for the Henkel family to erect a post office, store, and school located at the crossroads at Wood's Ferry, Green County, Tennessee; his regret that Samuel will not visit soon, his hopes of finishing his studies so he might be a candidate for the position at the New Market Academy, his "medical practice," the need of copies of the Concordia and other books
    - Samuel G. Henkel, 1835-1857 (Box Box 1)
      re his criticism of Professor Samuel Schmucker's Popular Theology because of its deviation from the fundamental doctrines of the Lutheran Church and the General Synod, the birth of his son Casper Coiner Henkel, and and Rev. Charles Henkel's translation of the Augustan Confession (1835); the republication of the works of David Henkel, and the impracticality of using agents to sell their books (1836); a strange medical case (1843); a request that the son of Hannah Stirewalt be admitted to the University of Virginia (1848); the translation of the Book of Concord (1849); the Book of Concord about to be bound, and his annoyance with the teaching of Professor Schmucker (1851); and recommendations to the Tennessee Synod meeting in 1857.
    - Silon A. Henkel to Samuel G. Henkel, 1838 Jan 7 (Box Box 1)
      re his medical studies in Philadelphia
    - Solomon Henkel* to Samuel Henkel, 1826, n.d. (Box Box 1)
    - Susan Henkel to Samuel Henkel, 1833 Mar 20 (Box Box 1)
    - Christian Jacob Hutter* to Solomon Henkel, 1815 May 13 (Box Box 1)
      offer of this bookseller to send a catalog of medical books, his plans to travel to Europe in eight weeks and his offer to visit friends and acquaintances of Solomon Henkel
    - E.H. Kohn to C.W. Bennick, 1896 Dec 23 (Box Box 1)
      re the salary for a minister at New Market
    - [Gideon ?] Koiner to Susan Henkel, 1840 (Box Box 1)
      re a gift from her mother
    - John Kolop* to Ambrose Henkel, 1809 Dec [9] (Box Box 1)
      list of subscribers for Henkel Press Song Book in Pendleton and Hardy Counties
    - Jacob Laros* to Solomon Henkel, 1812 Jul 17 (Box Box 1)
      questions re content of the catechism, symptoms of his sick wife, praise of Paul Henkel's work in Ohio, possibility of moving to Brush Creek Church, Highland County
    - Jonathan Leatherman to Solomon Henkel, 1810 Sep 24 (Box Box 1)
      re request to study medical practice with him
    - Theobald Lentz* to Solomon Henkel, 1805-1806 (Box Box 1)
      land transaction in the area of Salisbury, North Carolina, with the signatures of witnesses (1805) and questions re payment for land (1806)
    - William D. Lepper* to Ambrose Henkel, 1811 Oct 14 (Box Box 1)
      request to engrave the plates for Baron Steuben's "Regulations for the Order and Discipline of the Troops of the United States," with sample plates (formerly) enclosed, and immediate reply needed
    - C. Lindenberger to Solomon Henkel, 1815 Jun 19 (Box Box 1)
      re a letter possibly mailed to New Market, Virginia by mistake
    - D.L. [Mannhardt]* to Solomon Henkel, 1808 Aug 15 (Box Box 1)
      proposal to sell Henkel Press ABC books in Philadelphia by means of subscriptions
    - Lewis Markert* to Solomon Henkel, 1808-1813 (Box Box 1)
      request for books, especially the new ABC book (1808 Apr 9); note that the ABC books are selling well, request's Helmuth's Spelling Book and medical advice (1809 Apr 23); list of subcribers for 170 Song Books (1809 Dec 16); two pages of brief Biblical interpretations, and more subscribers for Song Books (1810 Feb 10); request that Paul Henkel come to North Carolina to help Pastor Schober with difficulties in his congregation (1810 Sep 5); demand for the Song Book and ABC books, intention of traveling to Kentucky and Ohio and visiting New Market on his return, and his work on a Children's Book (1811 Mar 27); description of trip to Ohio, his travels through Tennessee and Kentucky, the great influx of Baptists in Ohio, the need for both German and English Catechisms, Song Books, and ABC books, and the need for Paul Henkel in Ohio (1811 Aug 27); his return from Ohio, translation work on "Ein Briefwechsel die Methodisten betreffend" (1811 Dec 16); need for more books translated into English, plans another trip with Paul Henkel to Ohio, and worries re the War and conscription (1812 Jun 13); and his desire to travel but not teach school children, difficulties in North Carolina re the Song Books and Catechism, hints of a split among congregations (1813 Jan 4)
    - John William Meyer* to Ambrose and Solomon Henkel, 1809-1810 (Box Box 1)
      list of officers and elders in Bottetourt County (1809); and request for the name and address of the present secretary of the German Evangelical Ministry (Ministerium)
    - Salmon S. Miles to Solomon Henkel, 1839 Jul 19 (Box Box 1)
      report re steam driven printing presses in New York and Philadelphia
    - Adam Miller* to Ambrose and Solomon Henkel, 1816-1818 (Box Box 1)
      request for English Catechisms, also Conference Reports (1816); account of books and difficulties in selling books (1817); good reception of the new ABC books in Tennessee (1818)
    - Daniel Moser* to Solomon Henkel, 1818 Jan 30 (Box Box 1)
      troubles re the survival of the German [language], and good reception of the new ABC books
    - Jonathan R. Moser to Samuel G. Henkel, 1838 Feb 28 (Box Box 1)
      re arrangements to purchase books for the brethren in North Carolina
    - Yost Muetze* to Solomon Henkel, 1822 Oct 1 (Box Box 1)
      synodical difficulties in North and South Carolina
    - Henry Muhlenberg* to Solomon Henkel, 1805-1807 (Box Box 1)
      advice re cancer cure using an arsenic solution, hydrophobia, recently acquired books for sale, book store started by Muhlenberg and his source for books, his interest in medicinal plants and names of plant dealers, Dr. John Brickel and Fr. Dahlman (1805); advice concerning herbs, and a list of eleven books with their prices sent to New Market (1806); financial accounts concerning Mr. Etter, Michael Lohr, and Heinrich Busching, and complaints re bills (1807)
    - Jacob Muller* to Ambrose and Solomon Henkel, 1810 Apr 10 (Box Box 1)
      request for medicine for a pastor's wife and a description of her symptoms
    - John Nehs* to Solomon Henkel, 1815 Oct 28 (Box Box 2)
      inability to sell books and his desire to return the 150 small books
    - John George Ney* [ Solomon Henkel ?], 1822 (Box Box 2)
      reference to previous letters, collection of bills, and the Bank of Alexandria
    - Henry Oberholzer* to Solomon Henkel, 1811-1812 (Box Box 2)
      report of his position as a teacher in Franconia Township near Philadelphia, request for twelve dozen ABC Books and a dozen other books (1811); and lack of a bill with the books received from the Henkels (1812)
    - Nancy Orbaugh to Solomon Henkel, 1810 May 26 (Box Box 2)
      the health of her son
    - John Ori* to Solomon Henkel, n.d. (Box Box 2)
      request for tobacco seeds from Virginia with instructions for planting, in return for seeds of European plants recently bought abroad
    - George Pflieger* to Solomon Henkel, 1816-1821 (Box Box 2)
      request for German-English and English-German dictionaries (1816 Apr 2); thankfulness for the books and gratitude for Solomon Henkel's work in the Church (1816 Sep 30); receipt of box of books in Christiansburg (1818 Sep 17); return of two damaged books (1818 Sep 28); difficult time to sell books (1821 Apr 8)
    - J. Plitt* to Solomon Henkel, 1820 Sep 21 (Box Box 2)
      reference to a delivery of a package with newspapers or pamphlets and the need for subscribers
    - Jacob Poikey to Solomon Henkel, n.d. (Box Box 2)
      re an order of books
    - [T ?].K. Rebenach* to Solomon Henkel, 1810 Oct 9 (Box Box 2)
      the need for Song Books and a misunderstanding re Special Conference attendance
    - G.H. Rupert and Jo. S. Rupert to Samuel G. Henkel, their cousin, 1827-1835 (Box Box 2)
      re his marriage to Susan Koiner (1832) and other family news
    - William Sadler to Dr. Henkel, 1834 Aug 8 (Box Box 2)
      re renting a plantation managed by Henkel and owned by Casper Koiner
    - Jacob Savage to Solomon and Samuel G. Henkel, 1842-1846 (Box Box 2)
      re his financial affairs, the settling of a debt in Virginia owed to James and Alexander Wray, the interest due on the bonds made out to Samuel Henkel, and settling a debt in Philadelphia
    - John George Schmucker* to Solomon and Paul Henkel, 1807-1821, n.d. (Box Box 2)